A Guide to the Sixth Mount Zion Baptist Church Archives1867-1993
Virginia Commonwealth University, James Branch Cabell Library
Special Collections and Archives, James Branch Cabell Library, Virginia Commonwealth University
Sixth Mount Zion Baptist Church Archives 1867-1993
Special Collections and Archives, James Branch Cabell Library, Virginia Commonwealth University
M 57
.36 linear feet
Sixth Mount Zion Baptist Church
Administrative Information
Access
Collection is open for use without restrictions.
Acquisition Information
Material donated to Special Collections and Archives by Sixth Mount Zion Baptist Church in 1994.
Biographical/Historical Information
The Sixth Mount Zion Baptist Church was founded by Reverend John Jasper on September 3, 1867 and was the first church in Richmond organized by an African American. The congregation originally met in an abandoned horse stable on Brown's Island in the James River. In 1869 the congregation purchased land on Duval Street located in what is now Jackson Ward. The core of the present church building was erected in 1885 by George Boyd. The 1925 remodeling of the church in the Gothic Revival style was done by architect Charles T. Russell and builder I. Lincoln Bailey. The church was listed on the National Register of Historic Places in 1996.
Source: Virginia Department of Historic Resources, National Register of Historic Places registration form, Sixth Mount Zion Baptist Church, 1996.
Scope and Content Information
The collection consists of an assortment of historical documents, programs, photographs, brochures and clippings concerning the church, its pastors and Jackson Ward.
Arrangement
The materials are in one box and arranged alphabetically.
Contents List
- Architects: photocopied pictures
- Architecture photocopied pictures
- Article The Antebellum Preacher photocopy
- Article John Jasper: Colored Prophet
- Article John Jasper: From Slave Preacher to Community Leader
- Article John Jasper: The Preacher Who Moved the Sun
- Article on John Jasper, from Great Negroes: Past and Present
- Article- Richmond Church now a Virginia Landmark
- Article- Sixth Mount Zion Baptist Church, Richmond, Virginia, has Practical Tips for Preserving History.
- Article- Strong Foundation
- Booklet-Anniversary and Re-dedication of Sixth Mount Zion Baptist Church, photocopy
- Booklet-A Celebration of 130 Years of Christian Heritage 1867-1997
- Brief History of Sixth Mount Zion Baptist Church
- Brochure-Sixth Mount Zion Baptist Church
- Bulletin-Sixth Mount Zion Baptist Church
- Calendar-Sixth Mount Zion Baptist Church
- Certificate-The Virginia Landmarks Register (photocopy)
- Christmas Card-Interior of Sixth Mount Zion Baptist Church
- Historic Marker-photocopy
- Historic Quilt-Picture
- Installation Exercises for Reverend Peyton
- John Jasper- Ev'budy got ter rise ter meet King Jesus in de Mornin(photocopy)
- John Jasper-Family Record (photocopy)
- John Jasper-Pictures (photocopies)
- Letter-Celebrating our 130th Year, 1867-1997
- Letter-Maintaining Historical Artifacts
- National Register of Historic Places Registration Form
- Pamphlet-Experience Historic Jackson Ward, Richmond, Virginia
- Pamphlet-The John Jasper Room
- Requisition Form
- Sermon- De Sun Do Move by John Jasper
- Sixth Mount Zion Homecoming Activities 1992-1997
- Installation Services for Rev. John E. Johnson 1993
- Oberlin First Annual Dr. Vernon D. Johns Memorial Program 1990
- Sixth Mount Zion 125th Church Anniversary 1992
- In Memory of Rev. Isaac James 1991-1993
- Historical Information: Church and Jasper